Flies. Chapter nine. A view to a death.
Over the island, the buildup of clouds continued. A steady current of heated
air rose all day from the mountain and was thrust to 10,000 ft. Revolving
masses of gas piled up the static until the air was ready to explode. By early
evening, the sun had gone and a brassy glare had taken the place of clear
daylight. Even the air that pushed in from the sea was hot and held no
refreshment. Colors drained from water and trees and pink surfaces of rock, and
the white and brown clouds brooded.
Nothing prospered but the flies who blackened their lord and made the spilt
guts look like a heap of glistening coal. Even when the vessel broke in
Simon's nose, and the blood gushed out, they left him alone, preferring the
pig's high flavor. With the running of the blood, Simon's fit passed into the
weariness of sleep. He lay in the mat of creepers while the evening advanced, and
the cannon continued to play. At last he woke and saw dimly the dark earth close
by his cheek. Still he did not move, but lay there, his face sideways on the
earth, his eyes looking dullly before him. Then he turned over, drew his feet
under him, and laid hold of the creepers to pull himself up. When the creepers
shook, the flies exploded from the guts with a vicious note, and clamped back on
again. Simon got to his feet. The light was unearly. The Lord of the Flies hung
on his stick like a black ball. Simon spoke aloud to the clearing. What else
is there to do? Nothing replied. Simon turned away from the open space and
crawled through the creepers till he was in the dusk of the forest. He walked
dreilily between the trunks, his face empty of expression, and the blood was
dry around his mouth and chin. Only sometimes, as he lifted the ropes of
creeper aside, and chose his direction from the trend of the land, he mouthed
words that did not reach the air.
Presently the creepers festoned the trees less frequently, and there was a
scatter of pearly light from the sky down through the trees. This was the backbone of the
island, the slightly higher land that lay beneath the mountain, where the
forest was no longer deep jungle. Here there were wide spaces interspersed with
thickets and huge trees, and the trend of the ground led him up as the forest
opened. He pushed on, staggering sometimes with his weariness, but never
stopping. The usual brightness was gone from his eyes, and he walked with a sort
of glum determination like an old man. A buffet of wind made him stagger, and he
saw that he was out in the open on rock under a brassy sky. He found his legs
were weak, and his tongue gave him pain all the time. When the wind reached from
the mountaintop, he could see something happen, a flicker of blue stuff against
brown clouds. He pushed himself forward, and the wind came again, stronger now,
cuffing the forest heads till they ducked and roared. Simon saw a humped
thing suddenly sit up on the top and looked down at him. He hid his face and
toiled on. The flies had found the figure, too. The lielike movement would
scare them off for a moment so that they made a dark cloud around the head. Then,
as the blue material of the parachute collapsed on, the corpulent figure would
bow forward, sighing, and the flies settle once more. Simon felt his knees
smack the rock. He crawled forward, and soon he understood. The tangle of lines
showed him the mechanics of this parody.
He examined the white nasal bones, the teeth, the colors of corruption. He saw
how pitilously the layers of rubber and canvas held together the poor body that
should be rotting away. Then the wind blew again, and the figure lifted,
bowed, and breathed foully at him. Simon knelt on all fours, and was sick till
his stomach was empty. Then he took the lines in his hands. He freed them from
the rocks and the figure from the winds indignity. At last he turned away, and
looked down at the beaches. The fire by the platform appeared to be out, or at
least making no smoke. Further along the beach, beyond the little river and near
a great slab of rock, a thin trickle of smoke was climbing into the sky. Simon,
forgetful of the flies, shaded his eyes with both hands and peered at the smoke.
Even at that distance, it was possible to see that most of the boys, perhaps
all of the boys, were there, so they had shifted camp then, away from the beast.
As Simon thought this, he turned to the poor, broken thing that sat stinking by his side.
The beast was harmless and horrible, and the news must reach the others as soon
as possible. He started down the mountain, and his legs gave beneath him,
even with great care. The best he could do was a stagger. "Bathing," said Ralph.
"That's the only thing to do." Piggy was inspecting the looming sky through his
glass. "I don't like them clouds.
Remember how it rained just after we landed?" "Going to rain again." Ralph
dived into the pool. A couple of little onins were playing at the edge, trying
to extract comfort from a wetness warmer than blood. Piggy took off his glasses,
stepped primly into the water, and then put them on again. Ralph came to the
surface and squirted a jet of water at him. "Mind my specks," said Piggy. "If I
get water on the glass, I got to get out and clean them." Ralph squirted again
and missed. He laughed at Piggy, expecting him to retire meekly as usual,
and in pain silence. Instead, Piggy beat the water with his hands. "Stop it!" he
shouted. "Do you hear?" Furiously, he drove the water into Ralph's face. "All
right, all right," said Ralph. "Keep your hair on." Piggy stopped beating the
water. "I got a pain in my head. I wish the air was cooler. I wish the rain
would come. I wish we could go home.
Piggy lay back against the sloping sand side of the pool. His stomach protruded
and the water dried on it. Ralph squinted up at the sky. One could guess
at the movement of the sun by the progress of a light patch among the
clouds. He knelt in the water and looked round. Where's everybody? Piggy sat up.
Perhaps they're lying in the shelter.
Where's Sam and Eric and Bill? Piggy pointed beyond the platform. That's
where they've gone. Jack's party. Let them go, said Ralph uneasily. I don't
care, just for some meat. And for hunting, said Ralph wisely, and for
pretending to be a tribe and putting on war paint. Piggy stirred the sand
underwater and did not look at Ralph.
Perhaps we ought to go, too. Ralph looked at him quickly, and Piggy
blushed. I mean, to make sure nothing happens, Ralph squirted water
again. Long before Ralph and Piggy came up with Jack's lot, they could hear the
party. There was a stretch of grass and a place where the palms left a wide band
of turf between the forest and the shore. Just one step down from the edge
of the turf was the white blown sand of above high water, warm, dry, trotten.
Below that again was a rock that stretched away toward the lagoon. Beyond
was a short stretch of sand, and then the edge of the water. A fire burned on
the rock, and fat dripped from the roasting pig meat into the invisible
flames. All the boys of the island, except Piggy, Ralph, Simon, and the two
tending the pig, were grouped on the turf. They were laughing, singing,
lying, squatting, or standing on the grass, holding food in their hands. But
to judge by the greasy faces, the meat eating was almost done, and some held
coconut shells in their hands and were drinking from them. Before the party had
started, a great log had been dragged into the center of the lawn, and Jack,
painted and garlanded, sat there like an idol. There were piles of meat on green
leaves near him, and fruit and coconut shells full of drink. Piggy and Ralph
came to the edge of the grassy platform, and the boys, as they noticed them, fell
silent one by one, till only the boy next to Jack was talking. Then the
silence intruded even there, and Jack turned where he sat. For a time he
looked at them, and the crackle of the fire was the loudest noise over the
droning of the reef. Ralph looked away, and Sam, thinking that Ralph had turned
to him accusingly, put down his nod bone with a nervous giggle. Ralph took an
uncertain step, pointed to a palm tree, and whispered something inaudible to
Piggy, and they both giggled like Sam, lifting his feet high out of the sand.
Ralph started to stroll past. Piggy tried to whistle. At this moment, the
boys who were cooking at the fire suddenly hauled off a great chunk of
meat and ran with it toward the grass.
They bumped Piggy who was burnt and yelled and danced. Immediately Ralph and
the crowd of boys were united and relieved by a storm of laughter. Piggy
once more was the center of social derision so that everyone felt cheerful
and normal. Jack stood up and waved his spear. Take them some meat. The boys
with a spit gave Ralph and Piggy each a succulent chunk. They took the gift
dribbling. So they stood an ape beneath a sky of thunderous brass that rang with
the storm coming. Jack waved his spear again. Has everybody eaten as much as
they want? There was still food left, sizzling on the wooden spits, heaped on
the green platters. Betrayed by his stomach, Piggy threw a picked bone down
on the beach and stooped for more. Jack spoke again impatiently. Has everybody
eaten as much as they want? His tone conveyed a warning, given out of the
pride of ownership, and the boys ate faster while there was still time.
Seeing there was no immediate likelihood of a pause, Jack rose from the log that
was his throne and sauntered to the edge of the grass. He looked down from behind
his paint at Ralph and Piggy. They moved a little farther off over the sand, and
Ralph watched the fire as he ate. He noticed, without understanding, how the
flames were visible now against the dull light. Evening was come, not with calm
beauty, but with the threat of violence.
Jack spoke. "Give me a drink." Henry brought him a shell, and he drank,
watching Piggy and Ralph over the jagged rim. Power lay in the brown swell of his
forearms. Authority sat on his shoulder and chattered in his ear like an ape.
"All sit down!" The boys ranged themselves in rows on the grass before
him, but Ralph and Piggy stayed a foot lower, standing on the soft sand. Jack
ignored them for the moment, turned his mask down to the seated boys, and
pointed at them with the spear. "Who's going to join my tribe?" Ralph made a
sudden movement that became a stumble.
Some of the boys turned toward him. "I gave you food," said Jack. "And my
hunters will protect you from the beast.
Who will join my tribe?" "I'm chief," said Ralph, "because you chose me. And
we were going to keep the fire going.
Now you run after food. You ran yourself," shouted Jack. "Look at that
bone in your hands." Ralph went crimson.
"I said you were hunters. That was your job." Jack ignored him again. "Who'll
join my tribe and have fun?" "I'm chief," said Ralph tremulously. "And
what about the fire, and I've got the conch?" "You haven't got it with you,"
said Jack, sneering. "You left it behind." "See, Clever! And the conch
doesn't count at this end of the island." All at once the thunder struck.
Instead of the dull boom, there was a point of impact in the explosion. The
conch counts here too, said Ralph and all over the island. What are you going
to do about it then? Ralph examined the ranks of boys. There was no help in
them, and he looked away confused and sweating. Piggy whispered. The fire
rescue. Who join my tribe? I will. Me? I will. I'll blow the conch, said Ralph
breathlessly. And call an assembly. We shant it. Piggy touched Ralph's wrist.
Come away. There's going to be trouble, and we've had our meat. There was a
blink of bright light beyond the forest, and the thunder exploded again, so that
a little started to whine. Big drops of rain fell among them, making individual
sounds when they struck. "Going to be a storm," said Ralph. "And you'll have
rain like when we dropped here. Who's clever now? Where are your shelters?
What are you going to do about that?"
The hunters were looking uneasily at the sky, flinching from the stroke of the
drops. A wave of restlessness set the boys swaying and moving aimlessly. The
flickering light became brighter, and the blows of the thunder were only just
bearable. The little onins began to run about screaming. Jack leapt onto the
sand. Do our dance. Come on, dance. He ran, stumbling through the thick sand,
to the open space of rock beyond the fire. Between the flashes of lightning,
the air was dark and terrible, and the boys followed him glamorously. Roger
became the pig, grunting and charging at Jack, who sidestepped. The hunters took
their spears, the cooks took spits, and the rest clubs of firewood. A circling
movement developed, and a chant. While Roger mimed the terror of the pig, the
little onins ran and jumped on the outside of the circle. Piggy and Ralph,
under the threat of the sky, found themselves eager to take a place in this
demented but partly secure society. They were glad to touch the brown backs of
the fence that hemmed in the terror and made it governable. Kill the beast, cut
his throat, spill his blood. The movement became regular, while the chant
lost its first superficial excitement and began to beat like a steady pulse.
Roger ceased to be a pig and became a hunter, so that the center of the ring yawned
emptyily. Some of the little onins started a ring on their own, and the
complimentary circles went round and round, as though repetition would
achieve safety of itself. There was the throbb and stamp of a single organism.
The dark sky was shattered by a blue white scar. An instant later, the noise
was on them like the blow of a gigantic whip. The chant rose a tone in agony.
"Kill the beast! Cut his throat! Spill his blood!" Now out of the terror rose
another desire, thick, urgent, blind.
"Kill the beast! Cut his throat! Spill his blood!" against the blue white scar
jagged above them and the sulfurous explosion beat down. The little onland
screamed and blundered about fleeing from the edge of the forest and one of
them broke the ring of biggins in his terror. Him! Him him! The circle became
a horseshoe. A thing was crawling out of the forest. It came darkly uncertainly.
The shrill screaming that rose before the beast was like a pain. The beast
stumbled into the horseshoe. Kill the beast. Cut his throat. Spill his blood.
The blue white scar was constant, the noise unendurable. Simon was crying out
about something about a dead man on a hill. Kill the beast. Cut his throat.
Spill his blood. Do him in. The sticks fell and the mouth of the new circle
crunched and screamed. The beast was on its knees in the center, its arms folded
over its face. It was crying out against the abominable noise. Something about a
body on the hill. The beast struggled forward, broke the ring, and fell over
the steep edge of the rock to the sand by the water. At once the crowd surged
after it, poured down the rock, leapt onto the beast, screamed, struck, bit,
tore. There were no words and no movements but the tearing of teeth and
claws. Then the clouds opened and let down the rain like a waterfall. The
water bounded from the mountaintop, tore leaves and branches from the trees,
poured like a cold shower over the struggling heap on the sand. Presently
the heap broke up, and figures staggered away. Only the beast lay still a few
yards from the sea. Even in the rain, they could see how small a beast it was,
and already its blood was staining the sand. Now a great wind blew the rain
sideways, cascading the water from the forest trees. On the mountaintop, the
parachute filled and moved. The figure slid, rose to its feet, spun, swayed
down through a vastness of wet air, and trod with ungainainely feet the tops of
the high trees. Falling, still falling, it sank toward the beach, and the boys
rushed screaming into the darkness. The parachute took the figure forward,
burrowing the lagoon, and bumped it over the reef and out to sea. Toward
midnight, the rain ceased, and the clouds drifted away, so that the sky was
scattered once more with the incredible lamps of stars. Then the breeze died,
too, and there was no noise saved the drip and trickle of water that ran out
of clefts and spilled down leaf by leaf to the brown earth of the island. The
air was cool, moist, and clear, and presently even the sound of the water
was still. The beast lay huddled on the pale beach, and the stains spread inch
by inch. The edge of the lagoon became a streak of phosphoresence, which advanced
minutely as the great wave of the tide flowed. The clear water mirrored the
night clear sky, and the angular bright constellations. The line of
phosphoresence bulged about the sand grains and little pebbles. It held them
each in a dimple of tension, then suddenly accepted them with an inaudible
syllable, and moved on. along the shoreward edge of the shallows. The
advancing clearness was full of strange moonbeam bodied creatures with fiery
eyes. Here and there a larger pebble clung to its own air and was covered
with a coat of pearls. The tide swelled in over the rain pitted sand and
smoothed everything with a layer of silver. Now it touched the first of the
stains that seeped from the broken body, and the creatures made a moving patch of
light as they gathered at the edge. The water rose farther and dressed Simon's
coarse hair with brightness. The line of his cheeks silvered, and the turn of his
shoulder became sculptured marble. The strange attendant creatures with their
fiery eyes and trailing vapors busied themselves around his head. The body
lifted a fraction of an inch from the sand, and a bubble of air escaped from
the mouth with a wet plop. Then it turned gently in the water.
Somewhere over the darkened curve of the world, the sun and moon were pulling,
and the film of water on the Earth planet was held, bulging slightly on one
side, where while the solid core turned, the great wave of the tide moved farther
along the island, and the water lifted softly, surrounded by a fringe of
inquisitive bright creatures, itself, a silver shape beneath the steadfast
constellations. Simon's dead body moved out toward the open sea.
Lord of the